Okay בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is ק"ח, kuf chet,
108. We pick up at the sort of middle-ish of middle bottom
of ק"ז עמוד ב. kuf zayin amud bet.
And it is, let's see, where are we? Actually, the first wide
line. בית שמאי אומרים. Beis Shammai omrim. Today is also Goldie Guttman's
יארצייט. yahrtzeit. I understand that Joe spoke at, and made a little
קידוש kiddush at the, כיבוד kibbud at the early מנין, minyan, and
the learning should be in her memory and her זכות. zechut. We
so we begin at the first wide line. בית שמאי אומרים לפניו.
Beis Shammai omrim lefanav. So בית שמאי Beis Shammai says that מיאון
miun is whether in his presence or not in his presence. I'm
sorry, בית שמאי Beis Shammai says מיאון miun is only in his
presence and only in a בית דין. beis din. And בית הלל
Beis Hillel says whether in his presence or not in his presence,
and whether in front of a בית דין beis din or not
in front of a בית דין. beis din. So the גמרא Gemara
says: תנא תנן בברייתא. Tana tnun b'rabaita. אמרו להן בית הלל לבית
שמאי: Amru lahen Beis Hillel le-Beis Shammai: ולא פישון הגמל? V'lo Pishon
ha-gamal? Behold this
person פישון Pishon the presumably camel driver. I don't think he was
a camel. Okay.
מיאנה אשתו שלא בפניו. mi-ina ishto shelo befanav. His wife did מיאון
miun not in his presence. So you see you can do it
not in somebody's presence. אמרו להן: Amru lahen: It's pretty hard because
camel drivers are away for a year at a time. So maybe,
I'm serious, so maybe it was very hard to do it in
his presence.
Not in the presence of the camel.
אמרו להן בית שמאי לבית הלל: Amru lahen Beis Shammai le-Beis Hillel:
פישון הגמל במידה כפושה מדד... Pishon ha-gamal be-mida kefusha madad... or כפושה...
kefusha... he measured in a like רש"י Rashi says like an
upturned measure, which basically we'll see what that means. לפיכך מדדו לו
במידה כפושה. L'fichach madadu lo be-mida kefusha.
Does that word come from כף kaf as in?
I don't know, רש"י Rashi says it means like I think like
overturned or the bottom of the barrel type of thing, I don't
get exactly what the idiomatic phrase means. לפיכך מדדו לו במידה כפושה.
L'fichach madadu lo be-mida kefusha.
Therefore they did the same for him. What does that mean? Meaning
he dealt with her improperly, they dealt with him improperly. What does
that mean? מדקא אכל פירי, Mi-deka achal perei,
because he ate her fruit. Meaning one of the reasons that we
said before, which was a concern of the rabbis, was that a
man would basically try to strip-mine the נכסי מלוג nichsei milug and
get, you know,
because he'd be afraid that the woman would do מיאון, miun, so
he would not take care of the property. So he did this
to her property, and therefore they made it possible, more possible for
her to do this to him. So the גמרא Gemara says: פשיטא
נשואה היא. Peshita nishua hi. So the...
I'm sorry, or maybe, I'm sorry, I made that wrong. מדקא אכל
פירי, Mi-deka achal perei, so the גמרא Gemara understands that that's what
it meant, that he sort of strip-mined her property. So the גמרא
Gemara says: If he's eating the fruit, פשיטא נשואה היא. Peshita nishua
hi. So that means that it's already after נישואין. nisuim. But that
raises another issue because בית שמאי Beis Shammai says that you can't
do because there's also the problem about doing מיאון miun after נישואין.
nisuim. So the גמרא Gemara says: ומי בית שמאי נשואה לא ממאנה?
U-mi Beis Shammai nisuah lo m'maana?
There's another problem about a נשואה nisuah doing מיאון. miun. So תרי
קטירי עבדו בה, trei kuteiri avdu bah, so they did with him
two literally knots. Meaning they did, you know, they did him,
they fined him or they acted against him in two ways. The
way בית שמאי Beis Shammai would say is it's true she was
נשואה, nisuah, it's true that it was שלא בפניו, shelo befanav, but
he was dealing with her so improperly
that they allowed or you know, at least with her property, that
they allowed her to do מיאון miun even though it violated the
normal rules. Which is pretty funny, you know, because I mean since
when do you just basically say: Oh okay, well we want to
be nice to you or whatever, he's treating you wrong, we're going
to let you do this even though halachically it doesn't work. So,
you know, I mean תוספות Tosafos says in תרי קטירי עבדו בה,
trei kuteiri avdu bah, he says: בירושלמי פריך, B'yerushalmi parich, asks in
the ירושלמי: Yerushalmi: ומי כל העושה דבר שלא כשורה מתירין ערוה שלו?
U-mi kol ha-oseh davar shelo k'shura mattirin ervah shelo?
Just because somebody acts inappropriately you say okay fine then we'll just
like poof, you know, make you, you know, divorced, or whatever, make
the wife not married to you. And then תוספות Tosafos sort of
says: ואין זו קושיא כל כך, V'ein zu kusha kol kach, like
the end of that תוספות... Tosafos... דאיכא למימר דקידושי קטנה דרבנן נינהו
ואפקיעו רבנן לקידושי מיניה. d'ika l'meimar de-kiddushei ketanah derabbanan ninhu v'afkinu rabanan
l'kiddushei minei.
Sure,
it's all rabbinic anyway, we can do what we want. But again,
it's pretty funny that on a case-by-case basis we would do this.
There are sometimes cases where the גמרא Gemara says by a case
where a man improperly married a woman, that איהו עבד שלא כהוגן
אנן נעביד ביה שלא כהוגן ואפקיעו רבנן לקידושין מיניה. ihu avad shelo
k'hogen anu na-avid bo shelo k'hogen v'afkinu rabanan l'kiddushin minei. Okay, that
he did improperly there, we're going to do הפקעת קידושין, hafk'at kiddushin,
but that's a case where the whole קידושין kiddushin at the outset
was improper and we didn't allow the קידושין kiddushin to take effect
from the very beginning. This is different. This is because he's dealing
with her improperly, we give her special rights according to בית שמאי
Beis Shammai to do מיאון miun in circumstances where she normally would
not have the right. Anyway, that's how בית שמאי Beis Shammai responded
to this counter-proof from בית הלל. Beis Hillel. Michael, you had something
interesting there you wanted to, you were saying?
Just to say that the word כפושה kefusha they say over here
is from איכה הכפישני באפר. echa hichafshani ba-efer.
Okay.
Turn you over. Okay. I think רש"י Rashi might have quoted that.
Yeah.
Well, this is to kind of people involved here.
So maybe he has some kind of a right, as it were.
Yes. You know.
Right. So but
she has the right to refuse. Right.
So but that maybe that's not what makes the... necessary for it
to be in his presence. Maybe the fact that it has to
be in his presence is his right.
Aha.
And so he's like waiving, you mean it's not a formality in
the act, it's not like in order to give a גט, Gett,
the גט Gett has to reach the woman, in order to do
קידושין, Kiddushin, the money has to reach the קידושין, Kiddushin, in order
to do a מיאון Miyun it has to be in his presence
like that it would actually define the mechanics of the act? You're
sort of saying it's more like just, you know, it's sort of
like you don't give testimony to somebody not in their presence. Like
it's somebody like best to protect his right. So, it's an interesting
way of thinking about it, but that wouldn't deal with the נשואה
Nesuah case though, with the other problem that the גמרא Gemara raises.
But it's an interesting way of thinking about the בפניו Befanav case.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: בית שמאי אומרים בפניו
ובפני בית דין, Beit Shammai Omrim Befanav Ubifnei Beit Din, it has
to be in the presence of the court, ובית הלל אומרים שלא
בפניו ושלא בפני בית דין,
Uveit Hillel Omrim Shelo
Befanav Veshelo Bifnei Beit Din, it does not. תנן התם, Tnan Hatam,
we taught over there, we raised this, we mentioned this earlier, החליצה
והמיאון בשלושה, Hachalitza Vehamiyun Bishlosha,
it's in סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, the משנה, Mishna, החליצה והמיאון בשלושה, Hachalitza Vehamiyun
Bishlosha, חליצה Chalitza and מיאון Miyun is three, which is the position
of בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. So מאן תנא, Man Tanna, who's the
author of that משנה? Mishna? Because מיאון, Miyun, חליצה Chalitza we know
about, but it says מיאון Miyun is three. So אמר רבה בית
שמאי היא, Amar Rabbah Beit Shammai Hi, it's בית שמאי. Beit Shammai.
אביי אמר אפילו תימא בית הלל, Abaye Amar Afilu Teima Beit Hillel,
נהי דלא בעו בית דין, Nehi Delo Ba'u Beit Din, when בית
הלל Beit Hillel says it doesn't have to be a בית דין,
Beit Din, it means it doesn't have to be a like a
real weighty בית דין, Beit Din, it doesn't need מומחין, Mumchin, people
with like, you know, with סמיכה, Semicha, אבל שלושה בעינן, Aval Shlosha
Ba'inan, you still need three. כדתניא, Kidtanya, which is not the implication
one gets in the משנה, Mishna, but okay. כדתניא, Kidtanya, like we
taught in a ברייתא, Braita, בית שמאי אומרים בפני בית דין Beit
Shammai Omrim Bifnei Beit Din ובית הלל אומרים בפני בית דין ושלא
בפני בית דין. Uveit Hillel Omrim Bifnei Beit Din Veshelo Bifnei Beit
Din. ואלו ואלו מודים, Ve'elu Ve'elu Modim, even though בית הלל Beit
Hillel says it doesn't need a בית דין, Beit Din, they both
agree, both houses agree, שצריך שלושה, Shezarich Shlosha, you need three. So
you see a ברייתא Braita makes it very clear that when בית
הלל Beit Hillel says you don't need a בית דין, Beit Din,
it does not mean you do not need three. רבי יוסי ברבי
יהודה ורבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון מכשירין בשניים,
Rabbi
Yose
Berabbi Yehuda Verabbi Elazar Berabbi Shimon Machshirin Bishnayim, they say even two
suffices. We had an opinion similar by חליצה, Chalitza, two or maybe
one or maybe no one, but anyway, here it says two. ואמר
יוסף בר מניומי אמר רב נחמן הלכה כאותו הזוג. Ve'amar Yosef Bar
Minyumi Amar Rav Nachman Halacha Ke'oto Hazug. As opposed to what we
said by חליצה Chalitza where we explicitly rejected the opinion of less
than three, here we are explicitly embracing the opinion and saying that
מיאון Miyun can take place with only two. בית שמאי אומרים תמאן.
Beit Shammai Omrim Teman. Now let's say can she do multiple marriages
as a קטנה Ketana and do מיאון Miyun every single time? ובית
הלל Uveit Hillel says yes, ובית שמאי Uveit Shammai says this makes
בנות ישראל הפקר, Benot Yisrael Hefker, makes them treated like, you know,
like trash or whatever, that they're just easily disposed of and so
on. Although it's interesting because here they're the ones that are freeing
themselves, it's not other people are, you know, the man is disposing
of her. But anyway, בית שמאי Beit Shammai says no, she cannot
do it multiple times. תמאן, Teman, she has to do מיאון, Miyun,
and then the language of the משנה Mishna is a little bit
confusing because the משנה Mishna says, what does the משנה Mishna say?
It says תמאן, מממאנת, וממתנת עד שתגדיל, Teman, Memama'enet, Umamtent Ad Shetagdil,
she does מיאון Miyun and she waits till she becomes an adult.
So it seems like don't get married until you get adult for
the second time, don't get married the second time until you become
an adult. And then it says ותמאן ותינשא, Veteman Vetinase, and then
do מיאון Miyun and get married. So why do you need מיאון
Miyun again? So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. והא
מיאנה חדא זימנא, Veha Me'ana Chada Zimna, she already was מממאנת Memama'enet
when she was a קטנה. Ketana. Anyway, that's only when מיאון Miyun
works is when you're a קטנה. Ketana. אמר שמואל עד שתגדיל ותאמר
רוצה אני במיאונין הראשונים. Amar Shmuel Ad Shetagdil Vetomar Rotza Ani Bemiyunin
Harishonim.
So this is a very bizarre idea that we haven't heard until
now, which is a person has to reaffirm their מיאון Miyun when
they become an adult. Okay, so
confirmation. Right. So בית שמאי Beit Shammai is saying she does מיאון
Miyun as a minor, maybe, I don't know, and then before we
allow her to remarry, we need to, you know, we don't want
there to be any question, we don't want all this, you know,
on and off and this and that, marry, מיאון, Miyun, etc. And
anyway, we want it to be like protected and make sure that
it's not treated trivially. So not only do we not let her
marry again, we need her to reaffirm her מיאונין. Miyunin. That's an
interesting idea. Okay. במיאונין הראשונים. Bemiyunin Harishonim. עולא אמר תרתי קתני. Ulla
Amar Tarti Katani.
No, no, no. The משנה Mishna is giving you two options of
what she can do according to בית שמאי Beit Shammai after she's
done מיאון. Miyun. או שתמאן ותגדיל ותינשא, O Sheteman Vetagdil Vetinase,
either do מיאון Miyun now and don't get married a second time
until you become an adult and then you could do קידושין. Kiddushin.
או, O, or there is an option to get married while you're
a קטנה Ketana again, but here's the way you'd have to do
it. או שתמאן ותינשא לאלתר, O Sheteman Vetinase Le'altar,
or if you want to get married again as a קטנה, Ketana,
you can do it on the condition that you do נישואין Nisuin
immediately. Meaning, if you want to now do it a second time
as a minor, do מיאון Miyun and do קידושין Kiddushin immediately followed
by נישואין. Nisuin. Why does that matter? Because according to בית שמאי,
Beit Shammai, after נישואין, Nisuin, what's the הלכה? Halacha? Can she do
מיאון Miyun anymore? No. So בית שמאי Beit Shammai does not want
two מיאונין, Miyunin, her to do מיאון Miyun twice. So if you
did מיאון Miyun once, you either wait till you become an adult
or if you really want to get married now as a minor,
fine, but do it to immediately with נישואין Nisuin and that'll block
the possibility of מיאון Miyun a second time.
ותמאן ותינשא. Veteman Vetinase. What? And how does it read in the...
ששתגדיל,
what is it? המשנה היא, אלא מממאנת וממתנת עד שתגדיל Ella Memama'enet
Umamtent Ad Shetagdil
if you want to get married again. או, O, ותמאן ותינשא, Veteman
Vetinase,
do מיאון Miyun and get and do a נישואין Nisuin right now.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
right, the ו Vav is read as an or, which often is
how it means. בשלמא עולא היינו דתניא עד שתגדיל ותנשא Bishlama Ulla
haynu detanya ad she-tagdil ve-tinasei או ותמאן ותנשא o ve-timan ve-tinasei
because it's an alternative, do a second, do a מיאון, miyun, you
know, either or do a מיאון miyun and get married and do
נישואין. nisuin. אלא לשמואל Ella l'Shmuel עד שתגדיל ותאמר מיבעי ליה. ad
she-tagdil ve-tomar mibaei lei.
It should have said she goes up and reaffirms her מיאון, miyun,
not does a מיאון miyun because she already did a מיאון. miyun.
It should have said reaffirms, according to the way שמואל Shmuel read
it. So the גמרא Gemara said, okay, קשיא, kashya, that's true, it
should have said that a little bit more clearly. All right, but
that is an interesting idea, בית שמאי Beit Shammai doesn't want it
to happen
twice, so either he never allows it, or if he does allow
it, he only allows it the second time with a נישואין. nisuin.
And the possibility that בית שמאי Beit Shammai requires an affirmation of
the מיאון. miyun. Next משנה. Mishnah. איזו היא קטנה שצריכה למאן? eizo
hi ktana she-tzricha l'maan? What is a מיאון, miyun, a young girl
that has to do מיאון? miyun? כל שהשיאוה אמה ואחיה לדעתה. kol
she-hisuha ima v'acheha l'daata.
So anyone that her mother and her brother married her off לדעתה.
l'daata. So here's a fascinating idea, right? If her father's marrying her
off, it's not—she doesn't have to be a knowing party in the
process, I mean, you know, she could be a one-day-old infant or
something. Whereas here
it requires her to be done with her knowledge and presumably
consent, לדעתה l'daata presumably also means consent. So if we're going to
give her mother and her brothers that power, we're not going to
sort of, you know, necessarily compromise her interests in the process and
we're going to make sure that she has consent. I will say
that רמב"ם, Rambam, when רמב"ם Rambam brings down this הלכה, halacha, he
really doesn't mention the mother and the brother. The רמב"ם Rambam makes
it sound like she can marry herself off as a minor, and
that also is a possibility, that basically the Rabbis allowed for קידושי
קטנה kidushei ktana without a father, whether it's the mother doing it,
whether it's she doing it herself, and even when it's the mother
and brothers doing it, it's together with her consent.
Okay. But everyone had to have mother and brothers—meaning דווקא davka both
of them or?
People don't—I haven't seen the פוסקים poskim like talk specifically, I guess
I think the sense is like whoever's in charge, but I don't
know, it's a good question. I would have to see if the
פוסקים poskim get into specifics there. But the רמב"ם Rambam drops mother
and brother, he just talks about her marrying herself off
as opposed to the
father which is שלא לדעתה. shelo l'daata.
Exactly. Okay. השיאוה שלא לדעתה אינה צריכה למאן. hisuha shelo l'daata eina
tzricha l'maan. If they did it without her consent, she doesn't need
מיאון. miyun. רבי
חנינא בן אנטיגנוס אומר. Rabbi Chanina ben Antignos omer. רבי חנינא בן
אנטיגנוס Rabbi Chanina ben Antignos says—most of us I think know him
from like פרקי אבות Pirkei Avot or something. כל תינוקת שאינה יכולה
לשמור קידושיה אינה צריכה למאן. kol tinoket she-eina yechola lishmor kidusheha eina
tzricha l'maan. If she's so young that she cannot watch her קידושין—like
kiddushin you give her, you know, money for קידושין kiddushin and then
she just drops it or loses it or whatever—she doesn't even—she's not
even of an age that she knows the value of something and
how to protect it and how to watch it, then that's not
considered a קידושין. kiddushin. So again, what's interesting is, and you have
that sort of idea also by גט, get, like יודעת לשמור גיטה
yodaat lishmor gita etc. So what's interesting is that you are having
her as a minor almost as an agent, a partner in the
process of קידושין, kiddushin, right? So it does mention her mother and
brother, but it also speaks about her consent and it speaks about
her being able to sort of receive the קידושין kiddushin as it
were, to protect it. So, you know, it is interesting that we're
conceptualizing her more as a participant in this act.
As a human being.
Yes! Exactly! As an agent in this process. Okay.
So she just walks off—exactly. רבי אליעזר אומר אין מעשה קטנה כלום.
Rabbi Eliezer omer ein maaseh ktana klum. Now רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
says
I don't buy this whole קידושי קטנה kidushei ktana thing when it's
not the father. Anything a minor does is not anything. Now notice
it's אין מעשה קטנה כלום ein maaseh ktana klum since until now
the משנה Mishnah has been moving to make it not just the
act of the mother and the brothers, but moving to make it
her act, her consent, her receiving the קידושין, kiddushin, he's saying if
that's what it is, then this whole institution is meaningless
because what—a קטנה ktana can't do any legally binding act. אלא כמפותה.
ella k'mefuta.
Her whole status is like a seduced woman. So he basically says—he's
not denying—it's a fascinating position—he's not denying that we establish this idea
that she could be married
and there's this concept of מיאון miyun etc., but he says we're
not creating a reality of like קידושין דרבנן, kiddushin d'rabbanan, which is
normally how we think about this. Basically what we're doing is, we're
letting them live in sin. Okay, that's what he's saying. Like the
Rabbis will tolerate them living together, okay, but we're not going to
recognize it as a קידושין דרבנן. kiddushin d'rabbanan. Not because we can't
like tolerate the man living with an underage girl—I mean that happens
when the father marries her off—but because if we conceptualize it as—since
there is no father, she has to be the one marrying herself
off, well that can't really work. So therefore, all this whole institution
is, is them living in sin, it's not a קידושין דרבנן. kiddushin
d'rabbanan. Okay. So of course the question is going to be then
who needs מיאון, miyun, but the consequences are going to be that
there's no aspects of קידושין kiddushin here. So all the things we
talked about before, does he get to eat the פירות, peirot, this
and that, although maybe נישואין nisuin he would consider—doesn't sound like it.
So there's none of that, okay? It's just we tolerate them living
together, no aspects of קידושין. kiddushin. And here's one implications of it
for רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. בת ישראל לכהן לא תאכל בתרומה. bat
Yisrael l'kohen lo tochal bi'trumah. If she's— is married off to a
כהן, Kohen, she cannot eat תרומה. truma. We don't view them as
being married. Or בת כהן לישראל, Bat Kohen l'Yisrael, or if she's
a בת כהן Bat Kohen married to ישראל, Yisrael, תאכל בתרומה, tochal
bitruma, she can continue eating תרומה. truma. We do not view them
in any way rabbinically as married. Okay, and then and then also
issues like we talked about before about the פירות Peirot and all
those types of things. According to him they are not married in
any way shape or form. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר, Rabbi Eliezer
ben Yaakov omer, כל הכובש הימנה האיש, kol hakovesh heimena ha'ish, any
time that she resists because of him, because of the man, כאילו
היא אשתו, k'ilu hi ishto, she's demonstrating that she's his wife. If
she- we'll see the גמרא Gemara means if she resists marrying another
man because she says I can't marry another man, I'm already married
to this guy, then that demonstrates that she's his wife. כל הכובש
שאינו מן האיש, kol hakovesh she'eino min ha'ish, if it's not because
of her relationship to him, כאילו אינה אשתו, k'ilu eina ishto, it's
not like she's his wife. So it's not at all clear what
he means and for what הלכה halacha that means, we'll see about
that in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. But anyway you do have this fascinating position, a,
of the משנה Mishnah which we would not have expected, which is
that it's not that the mother and brother really takes the place
of the father, to a large degree it's that she's participating in
marrying herself off, and to this point that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
says and therefore it can't really be a קידושין דרבנן. Kiddushin d'Rabbanan.
Okay, so we were here when we began where it said we
were doing this in memory of Goldie. I know that's where- yeah,
it says זכר נשמתה. zecher nishmata. אמר
רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, ואמרי לה במתניתא תנא, ve'amrei lei b'matnita
tana, says רב יהודה Rav Yehuda and something we taught in a
ברייתא: Braita: בראשונה היו כותבין גט מיאון. barishona hayu kotvin get mi'un.
Okay, this had come up yesterday, the language that they would use
in the act of מיאון. mi'un. So originally this is what they
would write in the גט, get, the גט get here would not
be the instrument of מיאון, mi'un, it would just be a record
of the מיאון, mi'un, but here's what they would write in the
record of the מיאון. mi'un. לא רעינא ביה, lo ra'ina beih, she
said to him I do not desire him, ולא צבינא ביה, v'lo
tzavina beih, and I don't want him, ולית אנא ביה להיתנסבא ליה,
v'leis ana beih l'hitnasva leih, I don't want to marry him. Okay,
like you know, what is this like- like כל חמירא, kol chamira,
right?
Okay, anyway, okay, so all these languages that I reject him. כיון
דחזו דנפישא דיבורא, keivan dechazu d'nafsha dibura, since they saw that it
was becoming very wordy, אמרי, amrei, they said wait wait we gotta
change the text. Why do we have to change the text? I
know. Okay, exactly. So top of קמא עמוד א, kuf-mem-aleph amud aleph,
why do we have to change the text? אתי לחלופי בגיטא, ati
l'chlufi b'gita, they'll confuse it with a גט. get. Now what does
that mean? They presumably- I would have thought it meant that they'll
think she's מגורשת. megureshet. You go through this whole long process of
writing out this- this writ of מיאון, mi'un, right, you'll think oh
sounds like you know maybe people will leave with the impression that
she's a גרושה gerusha and that won't be good obviously because of
כהונה kehuna and so on. רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot don't say
that. They say that what it means is is that some ignorant
סופר sofer will say- he- he was called to בית דין beis
din to write a גט מיאון get mi'un and he wrote out
this long language and then next time he's called to write a
גט, get, so a real גט גירושין, get gerushin, and he'll think
it's the same type of document and he'll write again- he'll write
a גט מיאון get mi'un for people for somebody who wants a
גט. get. Which is fascinating because of course a גט get is
the man divorcing the wife as opposed to the woman rejecting the
guy.
But wouldn't a גט get also be get much longer?
I know, I don't get it, I really can't understand this. Anyway,
תיקינו האי. tikinu hai. So right, so they established exactly the short
form. Here's the short form: ביום פלוני, b'yom ploni, on on such
and such a day, מיאנה פלונית בת פלוני, mi'ana plonit bat ploni,
the you
know רחל בת יעקב Rachel bat Yaakov did מיאון mi'un באפנא b'apana
in our presence. Okay, they don't have any other- they did the
short form. Again, it's pretty funny like how long was it initially,
how did you confuse it with a גט? get? I don't know.
תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: איזו מיאון? eizu mi'un? Let's- what is the
act of מיאון? mi'un? אמרה Amra she says: אי אפשי בפלוני בעלי,
ee efshi b'ploni ba'ali, I don't want so and so my husband.
Okay, אי אפשי בקידושין שקידשוני אמי ואחי, ee efshi b'kiddushin she'kiddushuni imi
v'achai, or she doesn't relate to the man, she relates to the
act of the fact that my mother and brother married me off,
I don't desire that, or
you know I- I don't want the marriage that they- that they
put me into. יתר על כן, yeter al ken, more than this,
אמר רבי יהודה, amar Rabbi Yehuda, אפילו יושבת באפיריון והולכת מבית אביה
לבית בעלה, afilu yoshevet b'apiryon v'holechet mi'beis aviha l'veis ba'ala, בית אביה
beis aviha here is לאו דוקא lav davka because her father is
dead but okay her father's household. Anyway, even if she is in
this like a wedding carriage right, what they did this whole fancy
ceremony bringing her to the חופה, chuppah, and there she is she's
being carried in the limousine from her father's house, right from her
father's house to the- to her husband's house and and there she
is while she's in the limousine she's saying: אי אפשי בפלוני בעלי,
ee efshi b'ploni ba'ali, I don't want this guy my husband, so
זהו מיאון, zehu mi'un, it could, even though you would say if
you really don't want him stop the car, get out of the
limousine. No, even if she's still in the limousine she can say
that and that works. יתר על כן, yeter al ken, more than
this, אמר רבי יהודה: amar Rabbi Yehuda: אפילו היו אורחים מסובים בבית
בעלה, afilu hayu orchim mesubin b'veis ba'ala, there she is she's in
her husband's house, she's been living with him and there are guests,
והיא עומדת ומשקה עליהם v'hi omedet u'mashka aleihem and she's there and
she's pouring the drinks, ואמרה להם v'amra lahem and she says to
them: אי אפשי בפלוני בעלי, ee efshi b'ploni ba'ali, I can't stand
so and so my husband I don't want him, so הרי מיאון,
harei mi'un, that counts. So the חידוש chiddush presumably is- רש"י Rashi
says the חידוש chiddush is it's not in the presence of a
בית דין. beis din. You know I would also say the חידוש
chiddush is that there she is she's functioning as a wife and
she's saying it, you know she's doing her wifely duties and she's
saying it and we say that's enough, she doesn't... Now of course,
at what stage is she just angry with him and say I
really can't stand him, but at what stage she's saying I don't
want to be married to him? Anyway, let me, let's just finish
this. Even that counts, okay?
יתר על כן אמר רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Yesser al ken amar
Reb Yose b'Rebbi Yehuda אפילו שיגרה בעלה אצל חנוני afillu shigrah ba'alah
etzel chanvani לגבות לו חובות משלו la'avos lo chovos mishelo even if
husband sends her to the storekeeper and says can you go ahead
and fetch my wallet? I left it at the store or something
that. ואמרה v'omrah and there she is at the storekeeper's and she
says have you seen my husband's wallet? אי אפשי ee efshi במי
שהלך bemi shehalach I really can't don't want can't stand, it's not
can't stand because that's not what she's saying. אי אפשי ee efshi
means I don't want, right? I don't want my
husband and she's complaining to the storekeeper because she was sent on
this little task, errand. אין לך מיאון גדול מזה. ein lach mi-un
gadol mizeh.
There is no bigger מיאון mi-un than that. That works. So fascinating,
first of all, what happened to the בית דין? beis din? רש"י
Rashi even points out that there's no בית דין. beis din. What
happens to the fact that maybe in the context,
A, she's doing a wifely task as it were, and B, maybe
there's reasons why she's frustrated? So it really shows you, I actually
have a hard time understanding it, but maybe it's somewhat similar to
רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer's point, it really shows you to some degree
at the same time when we created this institution, somehow we also
made it, wanted to make it very easy to be dissolved. And
how much I guess what it really reflects is the idea of
the משנה mishnah of מדעתה, mida'atah, how much we're empowering her, how
much we are giving her the ability to really dissolve it at
will. Yes, Michael, what did you want to say?
I understand the מדעתה mida'atah part, but we still said before that
even בית הלל Beis Hillel agrees that you need three. The question
was whether you need מומחין mumchin or not, right?
Right, so there רש"י Rashi points it out. I don't know. רש"י
Rashi says even though there's no בית דין, beis din, maybe he
felt, look, this is a תנא, Tanna, this is רבי יהודה, Rebbi
Yehuda, maybe רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda felt you didn't need a בית
דין beis din at all. But I would have said the חידוש
chiddush is not just the absence of בית... I guess you're true,
because the question of בית דין beis din is not just a
technical point. If there's a בית דין beis din present, even not
מומחין, mumchin, it means that you're acknowledging that what you're doing is
a legal act, rather than what you're just doing is like complaining
or sounding off. So that definitely is part of the חידוש chiddush
here. Even if it happen to be three guests, right, it's still
the חידוש chiddush not that there isn't a בית דין beis din
but they're not constituted as a בית דין beis din and you're
just... I understand, yes. So it could be technically you don't need
a בית דין beis din according to רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda. רבי
יהודה Rebbi Yehuda might be a different opinion. But there is a
but part of the חידוש chiddush is not just that they disagree
technically, but that it's not even acknowledged as a formal legal act.
It could be understood as just somebody who's just sounding off. Yeah.
And there's no חידוש chiddush that the ראשונים Rishonim say that there
were witnesses outside the store?
Right, right. So you could always constitute it that way. So part
of the question whether you need a בית דין beis din, or
not need a בית דין, beis din whatever, but part of the
חידוש chiddush is again that even though by context it could just
be somebody complaining, we're prepared to look at that as מיאון. mi-un.
Yeah, well I think what she said was really powerful. Normally we
might say דברים בעלמא, devarim be'alma, her actions speak louder than words.
Right. So here they're saying אין לך מיאון גדול מזה. ein lach
mi-un gadol mizeh. All her actions suggest she's the wife, but her
articulation is what reflects her will. Yeah. Yeah, it's true. Legally very
powerful. Yep. It seems to me like maybe these are we're looking
back in time. In other words, we're looking for something, if it
becomes determined did she do מיאון. mi-un. So let her say it
again. I mean, you want to know if she...
That's interesting. Right.
Maybe she already went to the בית דין Beit Din. and her
husband refused?
Ah, that's an interesting point. Right.
So you go back, well, in January, she went to the store
to pick up his wallet and she said what she said.
Right, right, right. That's a nice point because right, I was wondering
the same thing. Like, would this come back to bite her? Like,
if she said, "Aha, you did מיאון, mi-un, that's it." And she
says, "Wait, I don't want to do מיאון." mi-un. And he says,
"No, I'm gone. Goodbye. Who needs you? I don't want to be
married." So like, would this come... Right. So Sadoff raises an interesting
point. It's not necessarily that we would respond to this by saying,
"Oh look, you did מיאון." mi-un. But like, if we needed to
sort of identify an act of מיאון, mi-un, we could look back
at this and identify it as that. That's a very
interesting perspective on this. You know, because now she's an adult and
she can't do מיאון mi-un and we now, but it's in her
interest to say that she had done מיאון mi-un or a scenario
like that. Right, now her husband she's an adult and her husband
won't give her a גט get or something of that nature.
Yeah, but isn't this sort of like the same thing that, the
wife is a סוטה sotah and he lives with her again?
All right, we're not... Fine. I understand. We'll come up to this.
But could be that she hasn't lived with her again. Anyway, we'll
get to that later. Okay. רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס אומר כל תינוקת.
Rebbi Chanina ben Antignos omer kol tinokes. Now Rebbi Chanina ben Antignos
says that if she cannot watch her קידושין, kiddushin, again, another thing
making her part of the act, then she's not... then it's not
a good קידושין. kiddushin. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רב יהודה
אמר שמואל הלכה כרבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel
halacha k'Rebbi Chanina ben Antignos. We rule like him. תני, Tani, we
tanan in a ברייתא. braisa. Yeah, yeah. If the father, she's not
in the act at all. תניא קטנה שלא מיאנה ועמדה וניסת. Tanya
katana shelo miana v'amda v'nisas. So a minor girl that was married
off to a guy by her mother and brothers and she didn't
do a formal act of מיאון, mi-un, but then she went and
she married some other guy. So משום רבי יהודה בן בתירה אמרו
נישואיה הן הן מיאונה.
Mishum
Rebbi Yehuda
ben Beseira amru nisu'eha hen hen mi-unah. The fact that she went
and married off to another guy, that counts as a מיאון mi-un
to the first guy. Okay. איבעיא להו, Ibayah lehu, so they ask
the question, understanding the problem, right again about this נישואי הסתר. nisu'ei
hester. Right. I mean, it's true, she's choosing it, but she just
thought, okay, walk away, start living with another guy. Walk away from
him, start living with another guy. Every time she does it, okay,
it was a מיאון. mi-un. All right, but that’s what Rav Yehuda
says. Okay, נתקדשה מהו? nitkadsha mahu?
Now, איבעיא להו, ibaia lehu, נתקדשה. nitkadsha. Let’s say she only did
קידושין kidushin with a second guy, not נישואין. nisuin. Would the act
of קידושין kidushin count as a מיאון? miun? Because נישואין nisuin is
obviously much more serious; she started living with him. Okay, by the
way, it’s not just that she had sex with another guy, she
actually started living with him. I mean, she did קידושין kidushin and
נישואין. nisuin. Okay, but let’s say she only did קידושין, kidushin, what’s
the story? תא שמע, ta shema, קטנה שלא מיאנה ועמדה ונתקדשה. ktana
she-lo miana ve-amda ve-nitkadsha. So we have another ברייתא: braita: she didn’t
do מיאון miun but she went and she accepted קידושין kidushin from
another guy. משום רבי יהודה בן בתירא אמרו קידושיה הן הן מיאוניה.
mishum Rabi Yehuda ben Beteira amru kidusheha hen hen miuneha. That counts
as מיאון. miun. איבעיא להו. ibaia lehu. So now we ask the
question: פליגי רבנן עליה דרבי יהודה בן בתירא או לא? pligi rabanan
alei de-Rabi Yehuda ben Beteira o lo? So is רבי יהודה בן
בתירא Rabi Yehuda ben Beteira just voicing something that’s a consensus, or
is there an opinion of the רבנן rabanan that disagree and say
קידושין kidushin and נישואין nisuin of another guy don’t count as
מיאון? miun? אם תימצי לומר פליגי, im timtzi lomar pligi, and if
there is a debate about it, בקידושין או אפילו בנישואין? be-kidushin o
afilu be-nisuin? Would they only debate the קידושין kidushin scenario or would
they even debate the נישואין nisuin scenario, which is obviously a more
serious act of rejecting? ואם תימצי לומר פליגי אפילו בנישואין, ve-im timtzi
lomar pligi afilu be-nisuin, and if assume that they do argue on
both cases, הלכה
כמותו או אין הלכה כמותו? halacha kemoto o ein halacha kemoto? Do
we rule like רבי יהודה בן בתירא Rabi Yehuda ben Beteira or
not? ואם תימצי לומר הלכה כמותו, ve-im timtzi lomar halacha kemoto, and
if we do rule like him, בנישואין או אפילו בקידושין? be-nisuin o
afilu be-kidushin? Do we rule like him in the case where she
does נישואין nisuin with another guy or even קידושין? kidushin? So we
want to know all the various possibilities. All right, so all right
fine, אפילו בקידושין. afilu be-kidushin. Fine. תא שמע, ta shema, come in
here, אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, הלכה
כרבי יהודה בן בתירא. halacha ke-Rabi Yehuda ben Beteira. We rule like
him. הלכה מכלל דפליגי, halacha miklal de-pligi, and if we’re ruling like
him, presumably the רבנן rabanan argue. Now of course is it just
by קידושין kidushin or is it by is it just by קידושין
kidushin or even by נישואין? nisuin? So רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot
both say, I don’t know how they know but by context, that
since רבי יהודה בן בתירא Rabi Yehuda ben Beteira said two things
and he says הלכה, halacha, it means he’s פסקנינג paskening like him
in both ways. So we פסקן pasken like רבי יהודה בן בתירא
Rabi Yehuda ben Beteira in both ways, that even קידושין kidushin from
another guy is an act of מיאון, miun, and we’re assuming that
the רבנן rabanan disagree in both cases. Okay, דהכא איבעיא להו, de-hacha
ibaia lehu, fine, but we’re not done. We still have another question.
דהוה נסיבה מעיקרא או דהוה מקדשא? de-hava nesiva me-ikara o de-hava mikadsha?
In terms of her relationship to her first husband, when we say
accepting קידושין kidushin from guy number two is a מיאון miun from
guy number one, what was the relationship to guy number one? Was
it just a קידושין kidushin relationship or even a נישואין nisuin relationship?
Maybe if she had actualized her marriage with guy number one and
they’d started living together and it’s נישואין, nisuin, maybe we would demand
a higher level of מיאון. miun. So what’s the story there? תא
שמע, ta shema, come in here,
דכלתה דאבדין, de-kalata de-Avdin, the daughter-in-laws of אבדין, Avdin, אמרוד. amrud. They
now he has an interesting language as opposed to מיאון miun which
is reject, here it’s they rebelled. They rebelled, they rejected against their
husbands. They did מיאון. miun. Okay, so his sons, אבדין’s Avdin sons,
married these underage girls, okay, that were married off without a father,
and both of these girls did מיאון miun against his sons. Okay,
שדר רבי זוגא דרבנן למיבדקינהו. shadar Rabi zuga de-rabanan le-mivdakinhu. רבי Rebbi
sent a pair of רבנן rabanan to go check and to see
whether they had actually done מיאון, miun, which is interesting given the
earlier discussion, right? You
know, maybe he didn’t believe the people that communicated, that reported that
they had done this, or maybe getting back to an earlier discussion,
exactly, or maybe getting back to an earlier discussion, maybe he wanted
to see if they were serious about it or not, if they
were just complaining, right? That gets back to our earlier discussion about
does context matter or anything like that. Anyway, so רבי Rebbi sent
a pair of רבנן rabanan to check whether these young girls had
actually rejected their husbands.
It’s probably why I’m having such a difficult
time to debate them for that reason. Right, well, that could be,
that could be. Right, that’s a good point, that’s maybe part of
the function of בית דין. So אמרו להו נשי, amru lehu nashi,
so when these two רבנן rabanan were coming,
some of the women who said to them, to these girls, חזו
גברייכו דקא אתו. chazu gavreichu de-ka atu. They confused them and they
thought that these
were these women’s husbands. Maybe it was a case that they did
מיאון שלא בפניו, miun she-lo be-fanav, right? Maybe אבדין’s Avdin sons were
there with אבדין Avdin with רבי. Rebbi. So there they was, they
saw these two people coming from רבי’s Rebbi ישיבה, yeshiva, maybe, you
know, they thought these other women thought that they were these girls’
husbands. So they said, look, your husbands are coming. So אמרו להו,
amru lehu, so these girls said back to the women, ליהוו גברייכו
דידכו לנן לאו גבריינו. le-havu gavreichu didchu lanan lav gavreinu. Let them
be your husbands, who needs them, you take them. So אמר רבי
אין לך מיאון גדול מזה. amar Rebbi ein lecha miun gadol mi-zeh.
Oh, okay, we see they don’t want their husbands, so that counts
as a מיאון. miun. Now, that’s nice fitting into the earlier discussion.
It’s a little bit clearer than the case of the storekeeper complaining
to the storekeeper. Now, how is it relevant to us? מאי לאו,
mai lav, are we not talking דהוה נסיבה, de-hava nesiva, that they
were already had נישואין? nisuin? So you see that I don’t know
how he knows that. So you see that a low level of
מיאון miun is sufficient even by נישואין. nisuin. And if that’s true
by this verbal rejection, presumably it’s true by accepting קידושין kidushin from
another man.
It’s probably what
גברייכו, gavreichu, גברייכו, gavreichu, maybe it’s גברייכו, gavreichu, maybe, that’s interesting. But
the גמרא Gemara says לא דהוה מקדשא קידושי. lo de-hava mikadsha kidushei.
No, it was just קידושין, kidushin, you can’t prove, so anyway we
don’t know. So the גמרא Gemara says, bottom line, what do we
say? והלכה כרבי יהודה בן בתירא, ve-halacha ke-Rabi Yehuda ben Beteira, we
rule like רבי יהודה בן בתירא, Rabi Yehuda ben Beteira, ואפילו בנישואין
דקמא. ve-afilu be-nisuin de-kama. Even if there is נישואין nisuin with the
first guy. So we are very lenient in terms of מיאון, mi'un,
she could have a full נישואין nisuin with guy number one, and
at any small act we will be prepared to view as a
מיאון, mi'un, accepting קידושין kiddushin from guy number two, making some verbal
statement, who needs him, you take him, you like my husband, good,
you be married to him.
Okay, so anyway on that account, even if she's, it's נישואין nisuin
already to guy number one.
So the גמרא Gemara is making it very easy for a קטנה
ketanna to divorce her husband.
Exactly, yep. Okay, רבי אליעזר אומר. Rabbi Eliezer omer. Now רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says,
he rejects the whole idea that there's a rabbinic, if the women
are the ones that are engage, that are accepting the קידושין, kiddushin,
if the girls are the ones that are part of the act,
it can't create a real קידושין, kiddushin, even a קידושין דרבנן, kiddushin
d'rabbanan, and he basically says I'm only going to look at it
as like they're living in sin. Let's just finish this piece over
then I'll get your question. So אמר רבי יהודה אמר שמואל חזני
כל צדי חכמים, amar Rabbi Yehuda amar Shmuel chozani kol tzaddei chachamim,
it's an interesting phrase. I went and I inspected all the different
sort of angles, all the angles, all the different like positions and
nuances of the sages, ולא מצאתי אדם שהשוה מידותיו בקטנה כרבי אליעזר.
v'lo matzati adam she'hishveh midosa beketanna k'Rabbi Eliezer.
And there was nobody that was as consistent in their position as
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, right, cause you're dealing with a קטנה ketanna
and whatever, so to say like she's quasi-married, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
makes it easier, not quasi-married, she's nothing, she's living in sin. All
right. So שעשאה רבי אליעזר כמפייס עמו בחצר, she'assa Rabbi Eliezer k'mefayes
imo bechatzer, how does רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer look at the relationship?
It's like there they are, they're taking a walk in the garden,
you know, they're not married, זומת מחיקו, zomeis micheiko, and then they're
sleeping together, and then she arises from his bosom, you know, ותובלת,
v'toveles, meaning there they are they're in bed, they went on a,
they had a date, they went to bed, and then she goes,
ותובלת, v'toveles, and she goes to the מקוה, mikvah, ואוכלת בתרומה לערב,
v'ocheles bitruma la'erev, and she can eat תרומה truma even if she's
a בת כהן, bas Kohen, meaning she has no relationship, he's not
considered to be her husband to invalidate her from eating תרומה. truma.
The reason she has to go to the מקוה mikvah is after
they'd had sex, if the semen is coming out of her body,
it makes her טמא. tamei. So basically he's saying
we're going to allow them basically to have a live-in relationship, but
we're not going to acknowledge it in any way as a marriage.
I don't, doesn't seem so.
תנו רבנן רבי אליעזר אומר אין מעשה קטנה כלום,
tanu rabbanan Rabbi Eliezer
omer ein ma'aseh ketanna klum, the act of a קטנה ketanna are
meaningless, ואין בעלה זכאי, v'ein ba'ala zakai, and now we're going to
spell out the other implications, not just by תרומה. truma. Her husband
is not, does not, is not entitled לא במציאתה ולא במעשה ידיה,
lo bimtzi'asa v'lo b'ma'aseh yadeha, to
her earnings, the things she finds, like these are the normal rights
a husband would have at נישואין, nisuin, ולא בהפרת נדריה, v'lo b'hafras
nedareha, or to annul her vows, ואינו יורשה, v'eino yorsha, he does
not inherit her, ואינו מיטמא לה, v'eino mitamei lah, if he's a
כהן Kohen he won't become טמא tamei to her, כלל שדבר אינו
כאשתו לכל דבר, klal she'davar eino k'ishto l'chol davar, she's not his
wife in any manner, אלא שצריכה מיאון, ella shetzricha mi'un, but if
she wants to walk away she needs מיאון, mi'un, okay, which explains
why it's so easy to do מיאון, mi'un, cause basically all they're
doing is having a live-in relationship.
רבי יהושע אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua omer, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua goes to
the opposite extreme, בעלה זכאי במציאתה, ba'ala zakai bimtzi'asa, no,
it's her husband, he's entitled to her, to the, to her finds
ובמעשה ידיה, u'b'ma'aseh yadeha, her earnings, ובהפרת נדריה, u'b'hafras nedareha, and he
can annul her vows, ויורשה, v'yorsha,
he can inherit her, ומיטמא לה, u'mitamei lah, if he's a כהן
Kohen he can even become טמא tamei to her, which is fascinating
because דאורייתא d'oraysa she's not a כהן, Kohen, דרבנן d'rabbanan we let
him become טמא, tamei, the גמרא Gemara earlier said we treat it
like a מת מצוה mes mitzvah if you remember that גמרא. Gemara.
כלל שדבר הרי היא כאשתו לכל דבר, klal she'davar harei hi k'ishto
l'chol davar, the general rule
is she's completely like his wife, the opposite extreme, אלא, ella,
although she is fully like his wife, יוצאה במיאון, yotza bemi'un, I
allow her to walk away with מיאון. mi'un. So one says she's
not like his wife at all but if she wants to walk
away she needs מיאון, mi'un, and there's totally like his wife but
it's sufficient to do מיאון. mi'un. Okay, so let's see how the
גמרא Gemara continues to spell this out, or the ברייתא braisa actually.
אמר רבי נראין דברי רבי אליעזר מדברי רבי יהושע, amar Rebbi nirein
divrei Rabbi Eliezer midivrei Rabbi Yehoshua, says רבי, Rebbi, you know רבי
אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer position is more persuasive than
רבי יהושע's, Rabbi Yehoshua שרבי אליעזר השוה מידותיו בקטנה, she'Rabbi Eliezer hishveh
midosa beketanna, here's that language again, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer was consistent.
Right, how can you allow a woman that you're treating as a
wife to not need a גט? get? So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
at least was consistent. She's not a wife and okay, they're living
together, but she's not a wife. רבי יהושע חילק, Rabbi Yehoshua chiilek,
רבי יהושע's Rabbi Yehoshua making a distinction, מאי חילק, mai chiilek, what's
the, the inconsistency
of רבי יהושע? Rabbi Yehoshua? אי אשתו היא, i ishto hi, because
if you're really going to look at her like a wife, תיבעי
גט, tibaye get, like a wife need a גט. get. גמרא Gemara
says okay, רבי אליעזר נמי, Rabbi Eliezer nami, so what, there's a
similar problem by רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. אי לאו אשתו היא, i
lav ishto hi, if she's not his wife, they're just living together,
so מיאון נמי לא תיבעי, mi'un nami lo tibaye, why should she
require מיאון? mi'un? So the גמרא Gemara says אלא בכדי תפוק, ella
b'kadi teipuk, what, you want her to leave with nothing? You know,
you want her to walk away without doing anything? Which doesn't really
answer the question, but maybe it says look, I don't have to
look at it as a קידושין, kiddushin, you know, I could look
at it as a live-in relationship that needs some act to sever
it. I'm not going to call it קידושין, kiddushin, I'm not going
to call it, you know, פסאודו-קידושין, pseudo-kiddushin, I'll call it a, you
know, a civil union, no, civil union is already probably civil קידושין.
kiddushin. Before we had all these civil unions, you know, where we
had these פסאודו-קידושין, pseudo-kiddushin, they're just living together, but even if you're
living together, you need something to say goodbye, we're breaking up, we're
leaving, it's over. You don't just walk out the door, you say
that's it, it's over, I'm out of here! Okay? So for him
he says that's what it is, just something to formally acknowledge the
breakup. acknowledge that that we're stopping the relationship, but in the end
of the day, it's just a relationship, it's not a קידושין. kiddushin.
So that's what he says. You know what? That's a consistent position,
right? Okay, you need something to sever it or to acknowledge that
it's over, but it's not אישות ishus and therefore that suffices as
opposed to saying it's a rabbinic אישות ishus where מיאון miun suffices.
David, you wanted to say something before?
Oh, yes, it was just to note that this was the אבדן
Abdan who was referred to earlier in the דף, daf, so that
those daughters are part of that whole thing.
Who was the אבדן? Abdan?
אבדן, Abdan, he came up before. The daughters-in-law of אבדן Abdan who
had embarrassed רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי.
Rabbi
Yishmael b'rebi Yosi.
Right.
Oh, the אבדן Abdan was the same one whose
daughters, oh, the מיאון miun about, right, right, I'd forgotten about that.
Remember when אבדן Abdan embarrassed רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי Rabbi Yishmael b'rebi
Yosi and it says that his daughters-in-law did מיאון? miun? So here's
the story of his daughters-in-law, I hadn't put it together, you're right.
Here's the story of his daughters-in-law doing מיאון. miun. Okay. All right.
You know what? We thought this way.
In other words, did you break up with them?
Right, right. You don't just walk out, like it's gotta be clear
if you've been living together, there's gotta be some acknowledgment of a
breakup.
Right. But the point is, I mean, this is in
contrast to how difficult it is for the woman to get out
of her marriage, right? Exactly. But that's what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
is saying. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is saying is because it's so
easy for the woman to get out of this, I can't call
it a marriage.
Okay. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer. Interesting
thing is, we don't פוסקין poskin like רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. We
actually פוסקין poskin that it is pseudo-קידושין. kiddushin. Yeah.
Did you break up? This is often a context of, oh well
then we got back
together, but then you're not allowed to do that.
Well, according to בית הלל Beis Hillel you are, only according to
בית שמאי Beis Shammai you're not. Right, from בית הלל Beis Hillel
you could go back, right? Actually, that's going to be the next
משנה. mishnah. So let's take a look. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר.
Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer. Now, רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer
ben Yaakov had this cryptic statement. If holding back is coming from
her, then she's his wife. If it's coming back, excuse me, due
to him, she's his wife. If it's not coming back due to
him, she's not. What does this mean? היכי דמי עכבתא דמיניה דאיש
ועכבתא דלאו מיניה דאיש? Heichi dami akavta de-minei de-ish ve-akavta d'lav minei
de-ish? What does it mean? A holding back coming from him, from
the man, or not coming from the man? אמר רב יהודה אמר
שמואל: Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel: תבעוה להינשא. Tiv'uha l'hinnasei. So here
she is, she was married to guy number one, and guy number
two comes along and says to her, "I'd like, would you marry
me?" ואמרה. Ve-amrah. And remember before this is an opportunity to say
yes and do מיאון, miun, but here's what she says. She says
no to guy number two. Why does she say no to guy
number two? If she says, מחמת פלוני בעלי, Machmas ploni ba'ali, "I
can't marry you, I'm already married to guy number one," so זו
היא עכבתא דמיניה דאיש. Zu hi akavta de-minei de-ish. Then it's showing
you that he's holding her back because of her relationship to guy
number one. So therefore that is a non-מיאון miun and that's an
acknowledgment of the קידושין, kiddushin, you know, of the marriage to guy
number one. Okay.
זו היא עכבתא דמיניה דאיש, Zu hi akavta de-minei de-ish,
which he didn't need, right, but okay. Okay, זו היא עכבתא דמיניה
דאיש. Zu hi akavta de-minei de-ish. מחמת בני אדם שאינם מהוגנים לי.
Machmas b'nei adam she-einam mehuganim li. If she says, "No, I'm not
going to marry you, I don't like you, you're a disgusting person,"
okay, but basically she indicates her she would be prepared to marry
the right guy, even though she's already married to guy number one,
זו היא עכבתא דלאו מיניה דאיש, Zu hi akavta d'lav minei de-ish,
then she's not holding herself back because of her husband and therefore
we could look at it as a מיאון. miun. Now that's a
big חידוש. chiddush. Right? Just because theoretically she would say yes to
the right guy, doesn't mean that right now she's doing a מיאון.
miun. So תוספות Tosafot asks that question, and תוספות Tosafot says that
we're not talking about מיאון, miun, we're talking about the other line
in the משנה: mishnah: לדעתה או שלא לדעתה. L'da'atah o shelo l'da'atah.
Right? Remember we said it has to be with her, with her
consent. So how do you know it's her consent or not?
Meaning what, marrying what?
Meaning her brother and mother marry her off to guy number one.
They never asked her. Does she agree or not? Okay. And then
guy number two said, "Wait, so there's, you know, I'd like to
marry you." So she says, "No, I can't, I'm already married to
guy number one." That shows that she consented. If she says, and
it's a much better read, right, rather than a מיאון miun read.
If she says, "You know what? I'm waiting for a better offer,"
then it shows that she didn't consent. So this is a question
the way תוספות Tosafot reads it is what she says to guy
number two who proposes signals whether she consented to the marriage of
guy number one. Okay. Now, so that's the way he reads it.
אביי ורב חנינא בר אבין, Abaye ve-Rav Chanina bar Avin, דאמרי תרווייהו,
d'amri tarveiyu, so they both say, נתן לה גט זו היא עכבתא
דמיניה דאיש. Nasan lah get zu hi akavta de-minei de-ish. If guy
number one gave her a גט, get, then it shows and she
can't, you know, that shows that he's holding her back. He's not
free to marry somebody else.
She is? Because he gave her a גט. get.
Well, okay, but it shows that, but it shows that the first
thing was binding and it needed a גט. get. Okay, and what's
the implication, how's a גט get different than a מיאון, miun, you
say what difference does it make, how's a גט get different than
a מיאון? miun? Here's the implications. הוא אסור בקרובותיה והיא אסורה בקרוביו.
Hu asur bikrovoseha ve-hi asura bikrovav. If there's a גט, get, then
it means they were married and then divorced, so then they're forbidden
in one another's relatives.
Okay, ופסולה מן הכהונה,
u-psula min hakehuna, she's פסולה psula for כהונה, kehuna, she's a גרושה.
gerusha. היא קטנה
מיאנה בו, Hi katana me'ana bo, if instead of a גט get
she did a מיאון, miun, זו היא עכבתא דלאו מיניה דאיש, zu
hi akavta d'lav minei de-ish, it wasn't him holding back, right, she
was the one, it wasn't him who was determining her fate, she
was essentially determining her
fate. והוא מותר בקרובותיה והיא מותרת בקרוביו, Ve-hu mutar bikrovoseha ve-hi muteres
bikrovav, since there was no marriage, there's no problem of relatives now,
ולא פסלה מן הכהונה, ve-lo pasla min hakehuna, she's not an אלמנה
almana or פסולה. psula. So they basically read the issue of who's
holding back as a question of how did they break up? Was
it a גט get or מיאון? miun? So the גמרא Gemara says,
הכא תני לה לקמן, hacha tani lah lekaman, but that's the next
משנה mishnah where we're literally going
to. הממאנת באיש, hamemaenet beish, if you did מיאון, miun, הוא מותר
בקרובותיה
והיא מותרת בקרוביו.
hu mutar
bikrovoteha vehi muteret bikrovav. They were never married, so they can marry
the relatives, ולא פסלה מן הכהונה. velo pasla min hakehuna. נתן לה
גט, natan la get, if it was a גט, get, הוא אסור
בקרובותיה והיא אסורה בקרוביו, hu asur bikrovoteha vehi asura bikrovav, then they
are all forbidden in the relatives, ופסלה מן הכהונה, vupasla min hakehuna,
and then she is a גרושה gerusha who is פסולה psula to
כהונה. kehuna. So anyway, that is the exact next משנה. Mishnah. שזו
כפרושא דמפרש. shezo kefirusha demefaresh. The next משנה Mishnah is the explanation,
because it is literally the next line in the משנה Mishnah is
the explanation of this statement of רבי אלעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Elazar
ben Yaakov. So you can read רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar
ben Yaakov either the first way, which is how she refuses a
proposal to guy number two and is that a signal of her
consenting to the marriage to guy number one, not a מיאון, miun,
but a question of consent. Or you could just read it as
a question about how do they break up. Do they break up
with a גט get or do they break up with a מיאון?
miun? That determines whether or not they were considered to have been
married. Okay, and that is what the next משנה Mishnah is, so
let's read the next משנה.
Mishnah. So why is it another משנה?
Mishnah? That is the blame of the ווילנא, Vilna, you know, of
the Romm brothers. The גמרא Gemara did not break up the משנה.
Mishnah. Okay, so the גמרא, Gemara, the argument would be according to
that position, this should be the end of the previous משנה. Mishnah.
Okay, הממאנת באיש הוא מותר בקרובותיה והיא מותרת בקרוביו. hamemaenet beish hu
mutar bikrovoteha vehi muteret bikrovav.
So again, if it was מיאון, miun, they were never married, so
they can marry relatives now, ולא פסלה מן הכהונה, velo pasla min
hakehuna, she is not a גרושה, gerusha, she is מותר mutar with
a כהן. kohen. נתן לה גט, natan la get, if however they
were broken up through a גט, get, הוא אסור בקרובותיה והיא אסורה
בקרוביו, hu asur bikrovoteha vehi asura bikrovav, they cannot marry one another's
relatives because they were considered married and then divorced, ופסלה מן הכהונה
vupasla min hakehuna and she is a גרושה gerusha and cannot marry
a כהן. kohen. Okay, that is clear enough. נתן לה גט, natan
la get, and we are not going to talk about that, that
is discussed. נתן לה גט והחזירה, natan la get vehachzira, so he
gave her a גט get and then he remarried her, okay, which
you are allowed to do as long as she didn't marry somebody
else. ומיאנה בו, umiana bo, and then the second time around, she
did מיאון. miun. So there you go, getting together, breaking up, getting
together, okay. So there you go, so they got together again and
the second time and the בית שמאי Beit Shammai would not have
liked this. Although no, the first time was a גט, get, so
I don't know. Anyway, the second time you did מיאון.
miun. What? How do you bring her back? It is נישואין.
nisuin. Yeah, that is not clear. Anyway, we are not working with
בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. Anyway, then ונישאת לאחר, veniset leacher, after she
did מיאון miun with guy number one and broke up with him
the second time, she got married to guy number two. And
then ונתארמלה או נתגרשה, venitarmela o nitgarsha, and then guy number two
dies, okay. מותרת לחזור לו, muteret lachzor lo, she can go back
to guy number one. Now why can she go back to guy
number one? She is a גרושה, gerusha, right? Everybody understands sort of
the series of what happened? Okay.
Right, here is guy number one, right, and here she is, okay.
So step number one was גט, get, okay, then so that, then
she got remarried, and then step number two was מיאון, miun, okay,
and then that broke up, and then she goes ahead and she
marries guy number two here, okay, guy number two. Okay, we will
do I guess A and B, okay, and then after this, you
know, they break up, or he dies or whatever. And then so
and then she goes back and she marries guy number one for
the third time, okay. So now why isn't this a case of
מחזיר גרושתו? machzir gerushato? She was a גרושה gerusha here, here it
was okay to remarry her, she hadn't been married to another guy.
But by this stage, she had married another guy. It was a
גרושה gerusha from stage number one and he is allowed to remarry.
Why? And the answer is because this situation of מיאון miun redefines
her status vis-a-vis him. Even though she was his גרושה, gerusha, once
they remarried and did מיאון miun and because the nature of מיאון
miun is to undermine the קידושין, kidushin, even though you would say
it is only undermining קידושין kidushin number two, but the way sort
of רש"י Rashi explains it is it just makes it clear that
she is a קטנה ktana and this whole thing is a rabbinic
institution. So once basically she is re-undermining saying she was never married
to him because of the מיאון miun the second time around, it
makes it look at her status as though she was never married
to him period. So the magic is that because she did a
מיאון miun following a גט, get, it redefines her, it transforms her
status from a גרושה gerusha to have never been married to him.
And therefore, even after she marries number two, he can take her
back.
In other words, the גט get also retroactively
disappears like the marriage.
Right, except again what you would say is that the מיאון miun
makes the second marriage disappear, right? החידוש hachidush is that once she
has done the מיאון, miun, it redefines even the first marriage.
רש"י Rashi even sort of says it like אחרי שהוטמאה, acharei shehutmea,
but we don't really care about that.
But that's true anyway because first of all, this is all דרבנן.
derabanan. So I mean, this is no real קידושין, kidushin, right? If
somebody was sleeping with a woman and then she slept with another
man and then come back and marry whatever, so it's only within
those institutions that the תורה Torah is talking about, right? A קידושין
kidushin and then another one. Anyway, fine. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this,
מיאנה בו והחזירה, miana bo vehachzira, it started with
מיאון, miun, החזירה, hachzira, ונתן לה גט, venatan la get, the second
time around he gave her a גט. get. Then ונישאת לאחר, veniset
leacher, and then she married guy number two. ונתארמלה או נתגרשה, venitarmela
o nitgarsha, and guy number two died or whatever divorced her. אסורה
לחזור לו, asura lachzor lo, then she can't go back, because then
her most recent status with guy... guy number one was a גרושה.
grusha. And that status hasn't been right revised, right? Does everybody get
that? It's basically you go by the most recent status that she
had with guy number one. Okay? So if it was מיאון me'un
and then גט, get, she's considered a גרושה. grusha. גט get and
then מיאון, me'un, she's considered never having been married to him. Okay,
so then the גמרא Gemara continues.
Isn't it not a real marriage because it's rabbinic?
Yeah, in terms of the דאורייתא d'oraisa principle of מחזיר גרושתו, machzir
grushaso, right, you wouldn't be over the דאורייתא d'oraisa lav in these
cases because you never had a real דאורייתא d'oraisa marriage to begin
with.
But it's still a גט get is still a גט, get, right?
Right, like he's a גרושה grusha for a כהן, kohen, but again,
that's all מדרבנן. mi-derabbanan. דאורייתא d'oraisa
this none of this
she wouldn't have a problem at all, she was with guy number
one and then guy number two.
Let's go to the next page. זה כלל: Ze klal: גט אחר
מיאון, get achar me'un, if the גט get came second, אסורה לחזור
לו, asura lachzor lo, then she's defined as a גרושה grusha and
she can't go back to him. מיאון אחר גט, me'un achar get,
if the מיאון me'un came second, מותרת לחזור לו, mutteres lachzor lo,
she can go back to him. הממאנת באיש, Ha-mema'enes b'ish, now let's
say there are three
guys, הממאנת
באיש ונישאת לאחר וגירשה לאחר ומיאנה בו לאחר וגירשה. ha-mema'enes b'ish v'nisas
l'acher v'geresha acher u-mi'ana bo l'acher v'geresha. So basically here's what she
did. Okay? She did she was exactly this is exactly why בית
שמאי Beis Shammai is saying, this is exactly why I told you
you can't allow these cases. Okay? So guy number one, she broke
it up with מיאון. me'un. Okay? That was guy number one. Then
she went to guy number two and she got married and she
broke it up with a גט. get. Then she went to guy
number three and she got married and she broke it up with
מיאון. me'un. Okay? She's going to every she's getting married to a
lot of guys and every guy she breaks up but in a
different way. And then after all of this, she wants to get
back with one of them. Okay? So will it be a case
of מחזיר גרושתו machzir grushaso or not? Will we say, for example,
that oh if she did מיאון me'un here, then she can get
back with guy number two because that meant that she was never
married. So the גמרא Gemara is saying no, the מיאון me'un only
works when it comes after a גט get to redefine her status
with the same guy. Right? If with one guy she did גט
get and then מיאון, me'un, the מיאון me'un says that redefines it
like she was never a גרושה grusha of that guy. But if
she did גט get with guy number two and מיאון me'un with
guy number three, she's still a גרושה grusha for guy number two
and she can't right and she can't go back to guy number
two. Is that clear?
Could she go back to
guy number one?
She could go back to guy number one, yes.
Okay, so let's read that.
הממאנת באיש ונישאת לאחר וגירשה לאחר ומיאנה בו לאחר וגירשה.
ha-mema'enes b'ish v'nisas l'acher v'geresha acher u-mi'ana bo
l'acher v'geresha. זה כלל, Ze klal, so what's the story? כל שיוצא
הימנה בגט, kol she-yotza mimena b'get, anybody she got גט get from,
אסורה לחזור לו, asura lachzor lo, she can't go back even though
a מיאון me'un came later, it was a מיאון me'un with a
different guy.
במיאון, b'me'un, anybody she left through מיאון, me'un, מותרת לחזור לו, mutteres
lachzor lo, she can go back to him. And now the גמרא
Gemara will just spell this out. So אלמא, alma, by the first
case where she switches from being a גרושה grusha to not and
she can go back to guy number one, אלמא אתי מיאון ומבטל
גט. alma asi me'un u-mevattel get. The מיאון me'un from guy number
one that came the second time around undermined the גט get and
made her a non גרושה. grusha. That was the truth from the
first case but it was the same guy who did גט get
and מיאון. me'un. So how does that work in the second case?
רמינהו: raminhu: הממאנת באיש ונישאת לאחר וגירשה לאחר ומיאנה בו לאחר וגירשה
זה כלל כל שיוצא הימנה בגט אסורה לחזור לו במיאון מותרת לחזור
לו. ha-mema'enes b'ish v'nisas l'acher v'geresha acher u-mi'ana bo l'acher v'geresha ze
klal kol she-yotza mimena b'get asura lachzor lo b'me'un mutteres lachzor lo.
So the case we just read, אלמא alma you see לא אתי
מיאון דחבריה ומבטל גיטא דידיה. lo asi me'un de-chavrei u-vattel gite dide.
A second guy's מיאון me'un doesn't undermine a previous guy's גט. get.
So the difference is obvious. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, amar rav
yehuda amar shmuel, but it's fascinating that the גמרא Gemara first assumes
it's a contradiction. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל: amar rav yehuda amar
shmuel: תברה, tavra, you're right, break the משנה mishna in half. מי
ששנה זו לא שנה זו. mi she-shana zo lo shana zo. There's
a debate, the first half of the משנה mishna and the second
half. The first half assumes a מיאון me'un redefines her status even
if she was a גרושה grusha and the second does not. Now
there's an easier answer, which is what רבא rava said. אמר רבא:
amar rava: ומאי קשיא, u-mai kashya, what's your what's bothering you? ודילמא
v'dilma מיאון דידיה מבטל גט דידיה. me'un dide mevattel get dide.
His own מיאון, me'un, you know, if it's the same guy, the
מיאון me'un with him redefines the גט get that came with him
earlier. So it's the same relationship, so it can redefine it. מיאון
דחבריה, me'un de-chavrei, but somebody else's מיאון me'un לא מבטל גיטא דידיה,
lo mevattel gite dide,
doesn't undermine the גט get that he gave her. Okay, so yes,
I mean the whole thing is a big enough חידוש chiddush already
that she can redefine whether she got a גט get and whether
she was a גרושה. grusha. But it only works with the same
guy. She got a גט get with guy number one and a
מיאון me'un guy number two, it doesn't redefine her status with guy
number one. Okay, very obvious answer. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara but
the גמרא Gemara somehow, well for me it seems very clear just,
you know, conceptually obvious, like you know it's defining the relationship. The
גמרא Gemara wants to understand like what's at the heart of it.
Why are we sort of you know you know why would we
allow a מיאון me'un to redefine and why wouldn't we? So let's
take a look. ומאי שנא מיאון דחבריה דלא מבטל גיטא דידיה? u-mai
shna mi'un de-chavrei de-lo mevattel gite dide? The גמרא Gemara assumes that
in principle if מיאון me'un can redefine, it should even be another
guy's מיאון me'un should redefine. It makes it clear that she's a
קטנה ktana and therefore it should make it clear that the גט
get wasn't meaningful. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara thinks that even the
other guy's מיאון me'un could redefine and there's got to be a
specific reason why we're not going to allow it. So here's why
we're not going to allow the other guy... Anyway, so the גמרא
Gemara says that even the other guy's מיאון Miun could redefine and
there's got to be a specific reason why we're not going to
allow it. So here's why we're not going to allow the other
guy's מיאון Miun to redefine. איידי דמיקרבא ברמיזותיו ובקצוצותיו. eidi d'makaras bi'remi'zosav
u've'kitzo'tzav. She'd been married to guy number one, so she knows, or
guy number two, she knows like the way, she picks up on
his body language.
אזיל משבש ומייתי לה.
azil meshabesh u'meisei lah.
He's going to go ahead and ruin things. What does that mean?
So here's what happens. Okay, she gets a גט Get from let's
say she started with a גט. Get.
She gets a גט Get with guy number one. Okay, now she's
married to guy number two. Okay, now guy number one has a
little bit of חרטה charata and he'd like to be remarried to
her. Okay, so obviously it would be a problem of מחזיר גרושתו,
machzir grushaso, but if she does מיאון, Miun, she's never really like
a גרושה grusha to this guy, so she can, he'd be, she
because she was never married, excuse me, to this guy. If she
does מיאון, Miun, he'd be able to take her back, right? So
wait, is that right? Hold on, hold on one minute, I said
one minute.
No, no, no, no, I'm sorry, even after she's done מיאון, Miun,
she can't go back to guy number one. She's stuck with guy
number two. She can't go back to guy number one. So here's
the story though. If here's, here's the case. Okay, I'm sorry, she
did גט Get and then she did מיאון. Miun. So the question
is, why don't we allow the מיאון Miun to redefine the גט,
Get, say that she was never a גרושה grusha of guy number
one and she can go back? And
for me it makes total sense. Why should a different guy's מיאון
Miun affect your status? But the גמרא Gemara thinks that any מיאון
Miun should say, is an announcement that she was a קטנה ketana
and this whole thing didn't really bind, and any מיאון Miun even
from another guy in principle should redefine her
status and you need a positive reason why you're not going to
allow it to do it. So the גמרא Gemara is introducing the
reason why in principle this מיאון Miun should say she was never
a גרושה grusha and after מיאון Miun she can go back to
guy number one. But you know why we don't want to let
her do that? Because then guy number one, she'll be passing him
on the street and he'll be sending her some signals and body
language and whatever and indicating that she should go ahead and do
מיאון Miun so that he can go ahead and remarry her. So
we basically, if we allow this מיאון Miun to say they were
never divorced,
we're going to sort of give him an opportunity to ruin the
second marriage and to get her to try to come back to
him. So that's why we don't want to do it. Of course,
you'll say, so if that's true, right, why aren't we concerned in
the reverse case? Right, so here she gets מיאון Miun from this
guy, why don't we say that he's concerned that he'll send her
body language, etc., because the point is she can't, and that'll get
her to want to do it, but here it worked out that
she got a גט, Get, but she hasn't had anything, right? So
she goes ahead, she marries another guy, why aren't we concerned he'll
also send her some signals or whatever? She'll do מיאון Miun and
go back to him, right? If we're always concerned that he's going
to send signals and she'll go back to him, why aren't we
concerned if it started with מיאון, Miun, the same problem? So let's
see what the גמרא Gemara say, let's just read that and end
with that for today. So the גמרא Gemara says, ומאי שנא מיאון
דחבריה דלא מבטל גיטו דידיה איידי דמיקרבא ברמיזותיו ובקצוצותיו אזיל משבש ומייתי
לה. u'mai shena miun d'chaverei d'lo mevateil gitu deidei eidi d'makaras bi'remi'zosav
u've'kitzo'tzav azil meshabesh u'meisei lah.
He'll go and ruin her marriage with guy number two and bring
him back. So that's if we allowed the מיאון Miun to override
the גט. Get. She's in control here. If her מיאון Miun could
override this previous גט, Get, she'll do מיאון Miun and then she'll
be free to go back, and we're giving number one the ability
to ruin this relationship. So the גמרא Gemara says if that's true,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this, ומייתי לה מיאון
דידיה נמי לא לבטל גיטו דידיה דאיידי דמיקרבא ברמיזותיו ובקצוצותיו אזיל משבש
ומייתי לה.
u'meisei lah
miun
deidei nami lo levateil gitu deidei d'eidi d'makaras bi'remi'zosav u've'kitzo'tzav azil meshabesh
u'meisei lah.
So the גמרא Gemara says same thing in this case, actually his
own מיאון, Miun, actually I gave you a different example, right? He
gave her גט, Get, then she went ahead and married this other
guy, okay? I'm sorry, gave her גט, Get, then took her back
and did מיאון, Miun, okay? And then she went ahead and married
this other guy, right? We're going to let, if she cared to
do מיאון Miun and go back to him, right? Why are we
going to let her do מיאון Miun and go back to him?
He's going to signal her, have her do מיאון, Miun, go back
to him. So okay, very nice, he already did מיאון, Miun, it's
same as if there was no גט. Get. Meaning, why
are we going to let her go back? He's going to now
be empowered to ruin the marriage. So the גמרא's Gemara answer is,
הכא טיב שיב ולא משבש.
hacha tiv sheiv velo meshabesh. He already tried and it didn't work.
What does it mean he already tried and it didn't work? In
this case, she refused him. She wanted out and he wasn't able
to keep her in the marriage, so we're not afraid if she
wanted out and she's married to guy number two, he's going to
be able to bring her back. But if he rejected her, he
gave her the גט, Get, and maybe she wanted to stay in,
but he gave her the גט Get and then she married guy
number two, we're not going to let her do מיאון Miun and
go back because now he will persuade her to come back because
maybe she always wanted to be in the marriage in the first
place. So the גמרא Gemara explains in a very complicated way that
this is a concern. That whether he's going to be able to
persuade, be, have a leverage to ruin her second marriage. Whereas conceptually,
it's really an easier just formal idea. Your act of מיאון miun
can redefine your earlier relationship with this woman, or her act of
מיאון. miun. That's the same relationship, so it can be redefined. Somebody's
מיאון miun with a different guy cannot redefine her status with the
first guy. So I would explain it in much more formalist terms.
The גמרא Gemara is explaining it in terms of a practical concern
about leading to a ruining of a relationship. All right, to be
picked up tomorrow. We are falling a bit behind here.
This is a theoretical case, right? Can I
just ask?